A Finding Aid to the Exhibition Records of the Contemporary Study Wing of the Finch College Museum of Art, 1943-1975, in the Archives of American Art AAA.finccoll
Archives of American Art
Exhibition records of the Contemporary Study Wing of the Finch College Museum of Art
bulk 1964-1975
1943-1975
AAA.finccoll
Archives of American Art
20.4 Linear feet
The exhibition records of the Contemporary Study Wing of the Finch College Museum of Art measure 20.4 linear feet and date from 1943 to 1975, with the bulk of records dating from the period its galleries were in operation, from 1964 to 1975. Over two-thirds of the collection consists of exhibition files, which contain a wide range of documentation including artist files, checklists, correspondence, writings, photographs, interviews, numerous films and videos, artist statements, printed materials, and other records. Also found within the collection are administrative records of the museum, artist files, and papers of the Contemporary Wing's director and curator, Elayne Varian, which were produced outside of her work at Finch College.
Finch College. Museum of Art. Contemporary Study Wing.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical/Historical note
The Contemporary Study Wing of the Finch College Museum of Art, later called simply the "Contemporary Wing," was established in 1964 by the president of Finch College, Roland De Marco, as an extension the Finch College Museum of Art in New York City.
Its mission was to educate art history students at the Manhattan women's college who were interested in working in with contemporary art. DeMarco, himself an art collector, hired Elayne Varian as director and curator of the contemporary wing. DeMarco met Varian in the New York office of the prominent international art dealership Duveen Brothers, where she had worked since the mid-1940s, most recently as an art dealer. Varian received her art education in Chicago, where she studied art history and education at the University of Chicago, and took classes in film at the Bauhaus and in fine art the Art Institute of Chicago. Sensitive to emerging art movements in galleries and studios around the city of New York, as the contemporary wing's curator, Varian quickly established a reputation for thoughtfully conceived, cutting-edge exhibitions which were consistently well-received by the press.
Under Varian, the Contemporary Wing carried out a dual mission of showing work of living artists and educating students and the public about the artwork and museum work in general. Varian used the galleries to provide practical training to students interested in a gallery or museum career throughout its existence. For several years, she also maintained an assistantship position for post-graduate museum professionals to gain experience in the field, many of whom went on to careers in museums across New York State.
The Contemporary Wing's best-known exhibitions formed a series of six shows called Art in Process, held between 1965 and 1972. Each of the Art in Process shows took a different medium, including painting, sculpture, collage, conceptual art, installation art, and serial art, and brought the process of art-making into the gallery with the artworks in various ways. For example, for Art in Process V (1972), the show about installation art, the galleries were open to the public for the entire process of its installation, allowing visitors to watch the works take shape. Another show entitled Documentation (1968) exhibited artworks with documentation such as artist's notes, sales records, and conservation records, bringing to light the value of record-keeping in the visual arts. Two exhibitions entitled Projected Art were also innovative, with the first (1966-1967) bringing experimental films from the cinema to the galleries, and the second (1971) showing artists' processes via footage and slides of artists working. Another show, Artists' Videotape Performances (1971), involved both screening of and creation of works in the gallery using a range of experiments with recent video technology. The museum also participated in an experimental broadcast of an artwork entitled Talk Out! by Douglas Davis, in which a telephone in the gallery allowed visitors to participate in its creation while it was broadcast live from Syracuse, NY. Other exhibitions that showcased experimentation in art included N-Dimensional Space (1970), on holography in art, Destruction Art(1968), on destructive actions being incorporated into contemporary art-making, and Schemata 7 (1967), a show about the use of environments in contemporary art, whose working title was "Walk-in Sculpture."
Other popular exhibitions at the Contemporary Wing included shows on Art Deco (1970) and Art Nouveau (1969). Several shows mined the private collections of prominent contemporary art collectors including Martha Jackson, Betty Parsons, George Rickey, Paul Magriel, Jacques Kaplan, Josephine and Philip Bruno, and Carlo F. Bilotti. A number of exhibitions featured contemporary art from overseas including Art from Belgium (1965), Art from Finland (1973), Seven Swedish Painters (1965), and Art in Jewelry (1966), which featured mainly international jewelry artists. Retrospective exhibitions of Hans Richter, Hugo Weber, and James Brooks were also held.
Hundreds of contemporary artists were shown at the Contemporary Wing in the eleven years of its existence, including many who came to be leading figures in contemporary art, and some who already were, including Andy Warhol, Roy Lichtenstein, Mel Bochner, Eva Hesse, Lynda Benglis, Bruce Nauman, Robert Morris, Lawrence Weiner, Robert Smithson, Sol Le Witt, Dan Flavin, Philip Pearlstein, and Yayoi Kusama, to name just a few.
The Contemporary Wing and the entire Finch College Museum of Art shut its doors in 1975, when Finch College closed due to lack of funds. The permanent collection was sold at that time, and the proceeds were used to pay Finch College employee salaries. Elayne Varian went on to the position of curator of contemporary art at the John and Mabel Ringling Museum in Sarasota, Florida. She died in 1987.
Scope and Contents note
The exhibition records of the Contemporary Study Wing of the Finch College Museum of Art measure 20.4 linear feet and date from 1943 to 1975, with the bulk of records dating from the period its galleries were in operation, from 1964 to 1975. Over two-thirds of the collection consists of exhibition files, which contain a wide range of documentation including artist files, checklists, correspondence, writings, photographs, interviews, numerous films and videos, artist statements, printed materials, and other records. Also found within the collection are administrative records of the museum, artist files, and papers of the Contemporary Wing's director and curator, Elayne Varian, which were produced outside of her work at Finch College.
Administrative records include records relating to the general operation of the Contemporary Wing concerning fundraising, professional associations, budget, contact information for artists, donors, and lenders to exhibitions. Also found are records of the permanent collection of artworks acquired by the museum between 1964 and 1975 from contemporary artists and collectors of contemporary art.
Artist files contain basic biographical information on over 150 contemporary artists, with scattered correspondence, photographs, technical information about artworks, artist statements, and other writings. Artist files also include an incomplete run of artist questionnaires gathered by the New York Arts Calendar Annual for 1964.
Elayne Varian's personal papers include curatorial records, a course schedule and syllabus related to her teaching activities, and various writings. Curatorial projects documented in Varian's papers include three programs produced outside of Finch College, including a juried show at the New York State Fair in 1967, a film series at Everson Museum of Syracuse University, and an exhibition at Guild Hall in East Hampton in 1973. Several of Varian's writing projects involved interviews, which are also found in this series in the form of sound recordings and transcripts. Interview-based writing projects include individual profiles on Brian O'Doherty and Babette Newberger, and interviews conducted for an article on the artist-dealer relationship published in Art in America (January 1970). Dealers interviewed for the latter project include Leo Castelli, Virginia Dwan, John Gibson, Richard Feigen, Arnold Glimcher, Fred Mueller, Martha Jackson, Sidney Janis, Betty Parsons, Seth Siegelaub, and Howard Wise. Artists interviewed include Roy Lichtenstein, Adolph Gottlieb, and Charles Ross.
Exhibition files, comprising the bulk of the collection, document exhibitions held in the Contemporary Wing during its existence from 1964 to 1975. Types of records found in the series include exhibition catalogs, correspondence, loan agreements, lists, contact information, insurance valuations of artworks, photographs, biographical information on artists, clippings, posters, press releases, and other publicity materials. In addition to the rich textual and photographic records found for exhibitions, numerous audiovisual recordings are also found, some of which were made in preparation for an exhibition, some document mounted exhibitions, and others are artworks themselves or components of artworks exhibited in the galleries. Interviews with artists, dealers, and others involved in exhibitions include Alan Sonfist, Mel Bochner, Hans Richter, Ruth Richards, James Brooks and Janet Katz, Margaret Benyon, Irwin Hollander (transcript only), David Anderson, Doris Chase, Will Insley, Michael Kirby, Les Levine, Ursula Meyer, Brian O'Doherty, Charles Ross, Tony Smith, Douglas Davis, Jane Davis, Russ Connor, Les Levine, Michael Mazur, Paul Gedeohn, and physicists Lloyd G. Cross, Allyn Z. Lite, and Gerald Thomas Bern Pethick. Video artworks, recordings of performances, or components of multimedia artworks are found by artists Vito Acconci, Kathy Dillon, Douglas Davis, Dan Graham, Les Levine, Bruce Nauman, Michael Netter, Eric Siegel, and Robert Whitman. A film of the Art in Process: The Visual Development of a Structure (1966) exhibition is found, and video recordings of artists Lynda Benglis, Michael Singer, and Sam Wiener form as part of the documentation for the Projected Art: Artists at Work (1971) exhibition.
Existence and Location of Copies note
All of the sound and video recordings in this collection, and two of the motion picture films, have been digitized for research access and are available at the Archives of American Art offices.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Archives of American Art acquired these records from the Finch College Museum of Art after it closed permanently in June 1975.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with curator Elayne Varian conducted by Paul Cummings, May 2, 1975.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 4 series.
Series 1: Administrative Records, 1950-1975 (2 linear feet; Boxes 1-2, 22, OV 23)
Series 2: Artist Files, 1958-1975 (2.2 linear feet; Boxes 3-4, 22, OV 23)
Series 3: Elayne Varian Personal Papers, 1965-1970 (1.3 linear feet; Boxes 5-6)
Series 4: Exhibition Files, 1943-1975 (14.8 linear feet; Boxes 6-22, OV 24-25)
Acconci, Vito, 1940-; Anderson, David K., 1935-; Benglis, Lynda, 1941-; Benyon, Margaret, 1940-; Bochner, Mel, 1940-; Brooks, James, 1906-; Castelli, Leo; Chase, Doris, 1923-; Cross, Lloyd G.; Davis, Douglas; Dwan, Virginia; Feigen, Richard L., 1930-; Glimcher, Arnold B.; Gottlieb, Adolph, 1903-1974; Graham, Dan, 1942-; Hollander, Irwin; Insley, Will, 1929-2011; Jackson, Martha Kellogg; Janis, Sidney, 1896-1989; Kirby, Michael; Levine, Les, 1935-; Lichtenstein, Roy, 1923-1997; Mazur, Michael, 1935-2009; Meyer, Ursula, 1915-; Nauman, Bruce, 1941-; O'Doherty, Brian; Parsons, Betty; Richter, Hans, 1888-1976; Siegelaub, Seth, 1941-; Smith, Tony, 1912-1980; Sonfist, Alan; Weiner, Sam; Wise, Howard; Art dealers--New York (State)--New York; Gallery directors; Gallery owners; Interviews; Museum administrators--New York (State)--New York; Museum curators--New York (State)--New York; Museum records; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Sculptors--New York (State)--New York; Sound recordings; Transcripts; Video artists--New York (State)--New York; Video recordings
- Administrative Records, 1950-1975; Series 1; 2.1 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, 22, OV 23
  Arrangement note
  Correspondence, photographs, research, and printed material related to specific exhibitions is found in Series 4, Exhibition Files. A number of the artists represented in the museum's permanent collection are also documented in Series 2, Artist Files.
  Scope and Contents note
  Series includes records relating to the operations of the Contemporary Study Wing of the Finch College Museum, including correspondence, pamphlets, brochures, flyers, notes, clippings, contact information, records related to grant applications and grant projects, records relating to the museum's permanent collection, photographs, and research files on a variety of subjects. Also found is a radio interview from 1968 on one sound tape reel with the Director of the Contemporary Study Wing, Elayne Varian, about the mission of the gallery and its exhibition program.
  Permanent collection records include letters of acknowledgement to artists and other donors for donations of artworks spanning the life of the gallery, lists of acquisitions, and photographs of artworks, many of which are negatives. Note that the list of permanent collection artworks listed by artist only lists works acquired between 1964 and 1966.
  - Annual Report, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Associations, American Association of Museums, 1966, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Oversized material housed in Box 22, folder 1.
  - Associations, Artist-Tenants Association, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Associations, Concerned Citizens for the Arts, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Associations, Friends of the Finch College Museum, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Associations, Gallery Association of New York State, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
  - Associations, International Council of Museums, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Associations, New York City Department of Cultural Affairs, Artists Certification Committee, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Associations, New York City Museums Council, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Associations, Partnership for the Arts, circa 1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Brochures, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Budget Notes, circa 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Contacts, Artists, circa 1964-1975 (Box 1, Folder 16-18)
  - Contacts, Donors, circa 1964-1975 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Contacts, Lenders, circa 1964-1975 (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Gifts, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Records relate to non-artwork gifts.
  - Grants, National Endowment for the Arts, 1966-1975 (Box 1, Folder 42-48)
  - Grants, New York State Council on the Arts, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Grants, New York State Council on the Arts, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Grants, New York State Council on the Arts, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Oversized Item in OV 23
  - Grants, New York State Council on the Arts, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Grants, New York State Council on the Arts, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Grants, New York State Council on the Arts, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Grants, New York State Council on the Arts, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Grants, New York State Council on the Arts, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Insurance, circa 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Interview with Elayne Varian for the "Art in New York" Radio Series, circa 1968; 1 sound tape reels (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Interview conducted by Bernard Murphy, broadcast by WNYC in New York, NY.
  - Invitations, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Lists of Artworks and Lenders to Exhibitions, circa 1964-1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Museum Accreditation, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Museum Membership, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Notes, circa 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Permanent Collection (Box 2)
    - Acknowledgement Letters, Antonakos - Youngerman, 1964-1975 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
    - Correspondence, 1964-1973 (Box 2, Folder 19-21)
    - Lists of Acquisitions by Year, circa 1964-1975 (Box 2, Folder 22-25)
    - Lists of Drawings and Paintings by Artist, circa 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Paintings out of Museum, circa 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Photographs of Artworks, circa 1964-1975 (Box 2, Folder 28-32)
    - Photographs of Exhibition Installation, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Problems, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Photographs of Artworks (Not in Permanent Collection), circa 1964-1975 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Photographs of Unidentified People, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Possible Future Exhibitions, 1966, 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 37-40)
  - Research Files (Box 2)
    - Art Collections, 1964-1970 (Box 2, Folder 41-44)
    - Kasser Foundation, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Charles Gifford Dyer, 1950-1964 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      Contains correspondence detailing provenance and insurance valuation for Dyer's series of paintings of the Acropolis, then held by Wesleyan Library.
    - Conceptual Art, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Experiments in Art and Technology (E.A.T.), 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Tamarind Lithography Workshop, circa 1965 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Sculpture Garden, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Shipping Receipts, 1965-1966 (Binder 2, Folder 51)
  - Tax Exempt Certification, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Oversized Administrative Records, American Association of Museums Certificate from box 1, folder 2, 1968 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Administrative Records, Research Files, Experiments in Art and Technology (E.A.T.), from box 2, folder 48, 1969-1970 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Administrative Records, Grants, New York State Council on the Arts, from box 2, folder 3, 1969 (Box OV 23)
- Artist Files, 1958-1975; Series 2; 2.2 Linear feet Boxes 3-4, 22, OV 23
  Series is arranged in two sections, the general artist files, and the New York Arts Annual Calendar files. Varian's letters to galleries soliciting artist information are found in the 1964 correspondence of the Administrative Records in Series 1. Unsolicited letters with artist information enclosed can also be found in the correspondence files in that series. Additional records related to works in the permanent collection of the Finch College Museum are also found in series 1. Many of the exhibitions documented in series 4, Exhibition Files, also contain their own run of artist files specific to the exhibition, which tend to contain richer documentation than files in this series.
  Series includes a group of files created at the Contemporary Study Wing to be both a study collection for students of museum practice and a resource for exhibition planning, which are filed under the general artist files heading. The general artist files also contain documents related to contemporary artists whose works were in the Finch College Museum's permanent collection, and printed material on artists who were of interest to Elayne Varian. Many of the general artist files contain only one or two items, usually a résumé, exhibition announcement, and/or photograph of an artwork. A few of the files contain more substantial documentation, including multiple images of artworks, photographs of artists, correspondence, instructions regarding complex artworks, posters, publications by the artist, or artist's statements. Files for Jeff Dell contain 3 motion picture film reels (16 mm), two of which also have two videocassette access copies each (VHS and Digital Betacam). Where present, significant materials in the general artist files are noted in the folder listing.
  Also found is an incomplete run of questionnaires for the 1964 New York Arts Calendar Annual, which were completed by artists and often accompanied with printed material relating to exhibitions scheduled for that year. A letter explaining the donation of these records to the Contemporary Study Wing for their research value is filed with this set of records. Questionnaires are found for artists with surnames beginning with A through E, and M through S. The rest of the Arts Calendar questionnaires are not found in the collection. Occasionally artists represented in this part of the series also have a file in the general artist files.
  Existence and Location of Copies note
  The motion picture film "Happy Birthday Felisa" (1968), found in the file for artist Jeff Dell, has been digitized for reference use.
  - General (Box 3)
    - Cecile Abish, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Vito Acconci, 1969-1971 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Includes several performance works, including a typescript entitled "Private Piece for Elayne Varian" (1969).
    - Lee Adler, circa 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Josef Albers, 1964-1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Eleanor Antin, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Includes multiple postcards from Antin's "100 Boots" piece, as well as photographs and printed material related to other works.
    - Maggy Aldrich, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Oversized item housed in box 22, folder 2.
    - Marit Guiness Aschan, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Elisa Asher, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Mary Asher, 1964-1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Edward Avedisian, 1971-1974 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Will Barnet, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Jack Beal, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Siri Berg, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Henryk Berlewi, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      Oversized item in box 22, folder 2
    - Nell Blaine, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Seymour Boardman, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Mel Bochner, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Joe Brainard, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      Contains a copy of The Baby Book by Brainard and Kenward Elmslie
    - Warren Brandt, 1968, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Selma Brody, circa 1974 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Robert Bucker, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Sylvia Carewe, 1959-1968 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      Oversized material housed in OV 23
    - Claudia Carrel, circa 1968 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Enrique Castro-Cid, circa 1964-1970 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      Oversized item housed in box 22, folder 2
    - Doris Chase, 1967-1970 (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
      Contains extensive correspondence between Chase and Elayne Varian. Oversized clippings housed in box 22, folder 2
    - Minna Citron, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Ross Coates, circa 1968 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Adele Cohen, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - George Cohen, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      Oversized poster moved to box 22, folder 2
    - Rosalind G. Cohen, circa 1962 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Joseph Cornell, 1967-1973 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      Contains correspondence with the Estate of Joseph Cornell following Cornell's death.
    - Hanne Darboven, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Jaime Davidovich, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      Oversized poster with handwritten note housed in OV 23